Sudharaka Fernando

Software Engineer

☑ sudharaka.jayanath1999@gmail.com

**** 077 556 7376

in $\operatorname{LinkedIn}$

? Github

• Colombo, Sri Lanka

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Software Engineer with 2 years of industry experience and 4 years of freelancing experience. Proficient in Java, Spring Boot, JPA, Hibernate technologies and developing REST APIs with Microservices architecture. Has experience in working with Azure cloud and JavaScript, React, VueJS, HTML5, CSS, SQL and also NoSQL databases. Team player with good communication and leadership skills. Looking for a position where I can apply my technical skills along with my collaborative skills for development initiatives.

SKILLS

Backend Development: Java, Spring Boot, Python, FastAPI, Pydantic, Golang, R, Object Oriented

Database: MySQL, PostgreSQL, Hibernate, JPA, MongoDB, SQLAlchemy, Firebase Firestore

Frontend Development: HTML, CSS, JavaScript, React, Vue, Redux, Vuex, Material UI, Bootstrap

Deployment: Docker, AWS S3 + CloudFront, GitLab CI/CD, NginX, Digital Ocean, Firebase Hosting, Vercel

WORK EXPERIENCE

Associate Software Engineer | Java, Spring Boot, Postgres, VueJs, Python, FastAPI, Linux, Git, CI/CD

Vizuamatix, Colombo Aug 2023 - Dec 2024

FRMS - Risk Calculation Process

- Designed and developed the database (Postgres) architecture and service logic for dynamic Risk ratio calculation process
- Added seperate normalized tables to handle complex and simple ratios, integrated Nashorn Engine for expression evaluation in Java
- \circ System was able to handle recursively defined advanced financial ratios in IFRS 9 and produce 100% accurate outputs for tested financial ratios

FRMS - Service Logic Optimization

- o Optimized service layer logic to handle multiple database intensive api requests
- Examined the service logic and reduced iterative database calls using Java Maps and optimized the data processing using Java Streams
- The most resource intensive service logic was optimized by 38% and overall system efficiency increased 30%

ECL - User Management

- Developed the User Management module handling user authentication and authorization
- Used Microsoft Entra ID to handle roles and permissions and integrated with JWT in the backend
- o Developed the frontend, handling the permissions returned for the logged in user

Software Engineer Intern | Java, Spring Boot, VueJs, R, Linux, Git ECL - Dynamic Loan Table

Vizuamatix, Colombo Feb 2023 - Aug 2023

- o Developed the loan table with flexible filtration ability with search and sort adding for each table headers
- Designed the frontend table integrating custom CSS to Vuetify library table and designed dynamic query function in the backend to generate the SQL query according to the passed parameters from frontend
- All combined searching and sorting scenarios could be handled from this single endpoint

Freelance Software Developer | Java, Spring Boot, React, Flutter, Git, Python, Next

Jan 2021 - Present

- Developed backend services in Micro Service architecture, enhancing scalability and performance of distributed systems
- Built responsive web applications with React and Next.js, and mobile apps using Android Studio with Java and Kotlin, as well as cross-platform solutions using Flutter.

• Implemented projects in Python and C++, including machine learning and computer vision applications

EDUCATION

B.Sc. (Hons) in Computer Engineering

Nov 2019 - Jul 2024

Minor Specialization: Data Management

Faculty of Engineering, University of Sri Jayewardenepura

o GPA: 3.6/4.0

o Deans List 2020 - 1st Year 1st Semester & Deans List 2024 - 4th Year 1st Semester

PROJECTS

Mushroom Analyzer

Backend Frontend F

- Mushroom analyzer is an web application developed for mushroom farmers to handle their operations.
 It provides the interface to mange their pot stocks, daily mushroom production, operational and capital expenses, income and also it gives the chance to manage and oversee their profits.
- o Technologies Used: Java, Spring Boot, Hibernate, JPA, MySQL, React, Material UI

AeroExpress- Airline Reservation System

Github 🗹

- AeroExpress project is a distributed microservice project designed to handle high traffic volumes for airline operations, enabling users to book and view tickets, check flight schedules, and manage reservations with ease. The backend, built with Java Spring Boot, utilizes a load balancer for high availability and reliability, while Spring Security with JWT tokens ensures secure authentication and authorization. Each Microservice is connected to its own PostgreSQL database, and MongoDB manages media storage. The system uses Eureka Server for service registry, and the frontend is developed with React, Material UI, and integrated with Axios and TanStack Query for smooth API interactions
- o Technologies Used: Java, Springboot, React, JWT, Axios, TanStack, Hibernate, JPA

Audio to Visual Feedback Converter for Weather News

Github 🗹

- This application is designed to help deaf people understand weather news with visual aid. The application has mainly three visual interfaces. Sign language avatar showing the Sinhala sign language interpretation, weather map which summarizes the weather news and AI generated video according to the weather news. The application was built using Python and Stability AI used for video generation. After audio was converted in to text using Google Speech API, the news was processed using NLP libraries like NLTK. For UI building PyQt5 was used
- o Technologies Used: Python, PyQt5, NLTK, Generative-AI, Stable-Diffusion, Tkinter

El-Care Github 🗹

- El-Care is a mobile application designed to assist senior citizens in managing their daily routines with ease. The app provides digital support for medical schedule management, emergency handling, sleep improvement, and connecting with family doctors to share medical information. Developed using Flutter and Dart, it features seamless integration with Firebase for real-time data management and SQLite for local storage. The app is optimized for Android devices, and Hive is used for lightweight data storage and caching.
- o Technologies Used: Dart, Flutter, Firebase, SQLite

CERTIFICATIONS

AWS Educate Introduction to Cloud 101 Software Architecture Foundations

AWS Educate LinkedIn Learn

REFERENCES

Dr. Udaya Wijenayake

Head of the Department – Faculty of Engineering University of Sri Jayewardenepura, Sri Lanka udayaw@sjp.ac.lk +94 76 465 5928

Mr. Pramuditha Sirisena

Senior Software Engineer Sysco LABS, Sri Lanka pramuditha.sirisena@sysco.com +94 77 819 9787